Well, hello.
So
in preparation for being able to do annotation
of a video element or an audio element or a
time text,
but being able to dynamically show
elements that are in the DOM based on time
code of the timed element,
before we can do that,
I think we need to actually go back
into thinking about how we might do overlays and dynamic content.
So one step at a time, we'll
look really briefly at the code,
we'll look at what it does,
and then spend a little bit more time
walking through it.
So border plate HTML here,
we have a title,
we have a body with a background color
that's dark orchid,
we have a video container and it's
the full width VW is a measurement,
you can use pixels,
you can use M's,
you can use percent.
I'm using viewport width and viewport height,
so it should fill the entire window.
You may not have seen this box sizing border box,
but that changes the box model of block
elements so that the width includes a border.
It includes so that otherwise if you have
a one pixel wide border on the thing,
it would actually extend beyond
the window, which we don't want.
I'm also using this CSS feature that
we haven't gone over called overflow.
And this controls what happens when things go
outside the bounds of the object or the element.
And by default,
they will keep going and extend,
you know,
into space and make your browser,
potentially your browser window get really wide or tall.
For reasons that will become clear later,
I'm saying actually if it goes out, anything,
if any,
the child elements of this element go outside,
don't show them at all.
Then they're inside this video container is a video element.
It fills that element.
And so it's basically going to be full screen.
And without truly being in full screen,
then I have some IDs that I associate with divs later in
the HTML for specific annotations will come back to these.
And then we've got this class here for Linus.
And that will make sense shortly.
In the HTML, we have our video container.
We saw the CSS forward already.
We have a video tag that's pointing at one of
my hearings from the Senate Intel Committee.
This one's from 2010. I've also got a track element here.
I'm not doing much with it,
but you should know like this is how you
include closed caption text or subtitles.
And I generated these using the
same tool I'm using for these talk through tutorials.
Then I've got one of my kind of annotation divs.
This one's called blur.
This one's called anno for annotation.
It's filled with the same text.
I should like, because they're not really stars.
What do you call those sparkles?
In the JavaScript,
we lay out a whole bunch of DOM objects.
We have an event listener listening
for when the video loads its metadata.
We have some timing functions here that should look familiar.
We change the current time.
We have an event listener.
We have a lot of things that we can do. This is our transition end.
We're not going to talk about that yet.
We're not going to talk about Linus.
Sleep should also be familiar.
I've used it in other code that you've looked at.
It waits a certain amount of time.
Returns a promise.
Let's look at what the code does.
I'm going to have to refresh here.
So it loads the video.
You can see we've got a border on the edge here.
When the video has
loaded, it waits and moves the playhead up.
Then we have these sparkles that turn into like poop
emoji and the background turns yellow and it spins around.
Then this blurred element appears.
All of these things are based on time from that sleep function.
They're not tied to the video behavior or to timestamps.
We're not doing that yet.
When I hit the play button.
Here we can use the closed caption and turn off the sound.
Every time I hit play,
Linus is going to dance across the screen,
including behind this blurry patch,
which blurs everything behind it.
I'm doing that for effect.
This is kind of hideous with the green border.
I'm going to play a couple more times
because I just like seeing this.
Okay.
That was fun.
I can just leave the video paused and watch them dance by.
Let's go back into the code here.
What's going on?
Okay.
So we have this loaded metadata event.
Means the video has started to load.
It hasn't done can play.
It hasn't done can play through.
But it has enough to set things up.
It waits five seconds and moves the play position because
the video doesn't actually really start for 18 minutes.
On this hearing,
it shows just a title beforehand saying like,
you know,
the hearing hasn't started yet.
Come down chill.
So I actually just advance it to where the content is.
We wait another second and a half and the video controls turn on.
Other words, I'm going to play this video.
Otherwise, we wouldn't have an easy way of
playing the video.
You can actually right click it and hit
play if there isn't another element on top.
And then annotate style top.
I'm changing the CSS of this annotate element
that I'm setting at the dominant here
to 50%. And that is the oval that is kind
of coming down from the top of the screen.
We're going to go back up and look at the CSS for that.
I'm using absolute.
In absolute positioning and absolute
positioning measures relative in absolute units
from the parent element.
The parent element is this full screen thing.
And so it's minus it starts out minus 50%
from the top.
So it means it's
like above the top of the screen.
It's off screen.
And it's 50% left.
I'm using this transform function to like better center it.
I'm setting the background.
It actually has a red green and blue value.
But I'm using RGBA and the alpha value is zero.
So it starts out transparent.
It has blue text in it.
But there's no text just emoji and emoji have their own color.
I'm setting the width by hand in pixels.
It's round.
Because I set a border radius.
The text is centered.
That includes the emoji.
And I'm using this new this new CSS
CSS function new for us.
And transition targets certain
kinds of functions.
You can see the documentation
is popping up here.
I'm targeting everything.
But if you only wanted to target positioning.
Like you could just
I'm the only thing that I'm really changing in the.
The main transition I'm doing here is the top.
Like positioning.
I can make this top.
And that would only target that.
I'm leaving it to to all because I'm also using it to spin.
I'm transitioning also on the transform.
So what you're targeting.
And I think you can set up multiple of these at the same time.
Like
separated by space.
So everything.
The transition takes five seconds.
And it eases in and eases out.
So it's rather than your choices are linear.
Which is like it will move.
Kind of at a constant pace.
Ease in ease out kind of like
speeds up and slows down at the end.
There's just ease in.
There's just ease out.
And then you can actually pass it like a complex.
Set of numbers for how you want the easing to work.
I've never found a reason to do that.
But it's there if you want to.
For more complex animations.
Maybe you have something that calculates that for you as a function.
And then there's the kind of a macho border around the oval.
Then we've got this blur element.
And I'm using Z index.
That changes the stacking order.
The higher the Z index,
the closer to the user it is.
Also a position absolutely.
Documentation for CSS filter.
There's a lot of different effects that you can apply to any element.
What's the difference between filter and backdrop filter is that.
The backdrop filter only affects things under the element.
Like this blur.
If there was text in the blur element.
The text itself wouldn't be blurred.
Everything underneath it would.
And at starting out with opacity zero.
There's a few different ways to make things visible or invisible.
Like changing the display from block to none.
We'll make it disappear.
Setting it from none to block will make it appear.
I'm using opacity because opacity is
something that works with transitions.
You can make opacity zero,
which is fully transparent.
It still exists in the space.
Of the webpage, you just can't see it.
Whereas when display is none.
It
doesn't really exist in the DOM.
I mean,
it's not entirely true,
but let's not go down that rabbit hole.
So a one opacity is fully opaque and fully visible.
And since I have a transition on all on this blur element.
It's just
the only thing I'm affecting with the transition is actually opacity,
but I'm lazy.
So I just wrote all because I kind of pasted it from above.
And then we've got Linus.
And Linus is a class, not an ID.
We notice we had lots of Linuses.
So use class for something where there's going to be multiple of it.
Use IDs for something that there's only one.
Linus also has a transition.
Takes five seconds for him to get across the screen.
And it's linear.
It doesn't speed up.
We slow down along the way.
And he starts out minus 40% off the left of the screen.
And based on the way it looked to me like,
I minus 40 was the point where you wouldn't see his right arm
when when he spawns.
So to speak.
And then I
changed the left value.
And then the transition runs.
So going back into the code,
we already looked at loaded metadata.
It changes the top positioning of the annotation.
And that's why it comes down from the top of the screen.
Now we have this other event listener that I'm applying to annotate,
which is the thing that comes down from the top of the screen.
And it's transition end.
And so this is an event listener that
fires every time a CSS transition finishes.
It's really useful to know when the thing is done.
You don't have to like
be calculating the time on your own.
Because sometimes these things don't actually.
Like there's a reason why it's better
to trust the event than the clock.
So transition end.
When it comes down from the top of the screen, it's not going to be a problem.
From the top,
it changes the text content to the hanky emoji.
It changes the background color to yellow.
From transparent,
these things are gradual.
Right. And it also changes this transform translate.
It keeps the new position
of the.
It does the transform changes a new transition fires.
And then this whole event actually happens again.
The rotate doesn't happen again because it like not
again again because like this actually stays the same.
It's setting it to this from this after the first time.
But then
since I have this counter here that's going up.
When it's finished the second transition.
Which is the five point, the five rotation turn.
From here.
It then tells the blur.
Element to transition.
It's a passity to one.
So that's why that kind of fades in at that point.
This is this is orchestration and action here.
I then make this function to sort of abstract
rather than doing it in the event listener.
This create line.
So I'm creating an event listener.
Image element in p5js you would use create IMG and straight
HTML and JavaScript use document create element.
I'm adding to its class list,
which are like CSS classes.
I'm adding line is to it.
So the CSS from from above affects it.
I'm setting its source to this file,
which is here in the same directory.
I'm appending the element to.
The video container is set up here to video container that div.
So it's
technically inside that div,
but it's outside of it because it's at minus 40% left.
And you don't have you don't can't scroll
to see it because of that overflow.
Directive that I added.
We wait this tiny amount of time.
Because if you want to see it, you can see it.
I was running into problems where if I tried to
change the position to off the screen on the right
side before it had really painted the element,
it would just go there and the transition wouldn't fire.
Some people do this with a set timeout window.setTimeOut function.
It was in the previous tutorial.
You can also do this with a sleep of
just like you can actually sleep zero.
Any any step will allow the element to like occur along an object.
So it's not for the transition to fire when you're
dynamically adding things to the DOM. Sometimes there's
this kind of weird timing stuff that can throw you off.
But
that's why we did it.
Then I'm adding an event listener to.
The Linus image that it
just spawned right that's the one I created here
and added to the DOM. When it ends that transition
when it gets off the screen to the right.
By Linus.
And.
It removes the element from the DOM so it doesn't exist anymore.
So this is something that
can allow there to be.
Hello Linus is.
As many times as.
This function gets called.
And you can see this is a slightly different
pattern than I've used previously of.
Add event listener rather than creating a nameless function here.
That has a bunch of stuff in it.
I'm just saying.
When the video plays.
Create Linus.
And you'll see that there's no like.
These parentheses.
That I just added are not there.
When you're passing a function.
You do it without the parentheses.
That's just that's just how it works.
I didn't I didn't write the language.
So that is how the program works.
Some tools here for thinking about how to use space.
How to move things from.
Invisibly sort of off the stage. So.
So to speak.
To appear on top you can.
Be really specific with like if you know how.
Large the video is.
You can position things relative to that.
Pixel by pixel.
Or you can kind of do something more vibes based where it's like.
I'm going to put something in the upper right
hand corner with a little bit of a margin.
We'll just look at the.
What that does one more time.
Starts the video at the zero position.
It moves it about 18 minutes in.
Just before the hearing starts.
18 minutes and eight seconds.
I can turn on these closed captions.
I can mute the audio because it's loud.
We got our little spinning thing five times.
We got our poop emoji.
And we got our blurry rectangle.
Here come all the lines.
I look how fast can I. I use the space bar
and you got like this line as army here.
Alright well you know smash that like and subscribe
button or whatever it is the kids say these days.
Thanks for listening and hope you learned something.